Guide to the Robert W. Floyd Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Robert W. Floyd papers
1960-1995
SC0625
Floyd, Robert W.
26 Linear feet
These papers include his Stanford course files, 1976-94; correspondence, 1968-95, including that with Donald Knuth, 1963-1987; research and subject files; reprints and manuscripts; computer printouts; and note cards. Some materials relate to his interest in backgammon.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of the estate of Robert W. Floyd, 2002.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Robert W. Floyd joined the Stanford faculty in 1968 as an associate professor of computer science. He was appointed full professor in 1970 and from 1973 to 1975 he was chair of the department. He retired from Stanford in 1994. A child prodigy, Floyd graduated from high school at age 14 and earned his first bachelor's degree at the age of 17 and his second in physics in 1958, both at the University of Chicago. A self-taught computer operator and programmer, he became a Senior Project Scientist at Computer Associates in Massachusetts in 1962. He taught at the Carnegie Institute of Technology prior to his appointment at Stanford. His most important scientific achievement was pioneering systematic methods of program verification. His research included design and analysis of algorithms for finding the shortest paths in a network, parsing (decomposing) programming languages, calculating quantiles, printing shades of gray on a dot printer, sorting information and selecting random permutations and combinations. In 1978, Floyd won the Association for Computing Machinery Turing Award, the highest honor in computer science. In 1991, the Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE) Computer Society awarded Floyd its Computer Pioneer Award for his work on early compilers. Floyd was a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, and the Association for Computing Machinery. He died in September 2001.
Description of the Collection
These papers include his Stanford course files, 1976-94; correspondence, 1968-95, including that with Donald Knuth, 1963-1987; research and subject files; reprints and manuscripts; computer printouts; and note cards. Some materials relate to his interest in backgammon.
Access Terms
Floyd, Robert W.; Knuth, Donald Ervin, 1938-; Stanford University. Computer Science Department.; Backgammon.; Computer programming.; Formal languages.; Machine theory.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2002-003
  - CS class files 1977-92 [needs review for grades, names, etc.] (Box 1)
  - CS class files 1985-94 [needs review for grades, names, etc.] (Box 2)
  - File titled "Rivest research" includes correspondence with Ronald Rivest 1970s (Box 2)
  - CS class files containing handouts, problems, assignments, etc, 1980s (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Donald Knuth 1964 (Box 2)
  - CS class files containing handouts, problems, assignments, etc, 1980s-1990/91 (Box 3)
  - Several files of text on Chiron language 1970s (Box 3)
  - Several files of text for chapters in Language of Machines, 1991 (Box 3)
  - File with one miscellaneous letter (Box 3)
  - Subject files containing papers by Floyd and others, research work, lectures, etc. (Box 3)
  - Subject files containing papers by Floyd and others, research work, lectures, etc. (Box 4)
  - Course files (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (Box 4)
  - Subject files (Box 5)
  - Course files (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, including some re his book Language of Machines (Box 5)
  - Floyd's reprints, by title A – CA, including some notes, correspondence, and typescripts (Box 5)
  - Floyd's reprints, by title CL – V, including some notes, correspondence, and typescripts (Box 6)
  - Four folders of loose materials, to be sorted (Box 6)
  - Correspondence files A – E, 1968-1993 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence files F – Z, 1968-1993, including separate files for correspondence with Donald Knuth, 1963-69, 1987 (Box 7)
  - Correspondence re Floyd's comments on articles by others (Box 7)
  - Subject and class files (handouts, problems, assignments, etc.) (Box 7)
  - Text for book and/or course syllabus, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Professional and administrative files, including Journal of the Association for Computing Machinery, National Science Foundation, Guggenheim Fellowship, Computing Reviews (Box 8)
  - File on S.U. curriculum (Box 8)
  - Some correspondence files, mostly re research (includes some Ph.D. students) (Box 8)
  - Loose materials put into folders (correspondence, articles, notes) (Box 8)
  - Research files (Box 8)
  - Class files (handouts, problems, assignments, etc.) (Box 8)
  - Research files (Box 9)
  - Class files (handouts, problems, assignments, etc.) (Box 9)
  - Files on awards (Box 10)
  - Local maps (Box 10)
  - Photos of interior of a house, ca. 1976 (Box 10)
  - Biographical files (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous professional/administrative files (Box 10)
  - Floyd's reader reviews (Box 10)
  - Publishers' files, including W. H. Freeman (Box 10)
  - Typescript of Floyd's "Notes on Programming in PASCAL," 1980 (Box 10)
  - "Papers" files containing typescripts, notes, and reprints largely of Floyd's work (Box 10)
  - Subject files (Box 10)
  - Large number of unlabelled files (Box 10)
  - Computer printouts: backgammon, Chiron, and others not labeled (Box 11)
  - Unlabelled files (containing mss notes, copies of articles, typescript text, some correspondence, and some class materials) (Box 12)
  - Loose material newly foldered – largely articles and reprints by others (Box 12)
  - Class notebooks (now in folders) largely containing computer printouts of material covered, problems, handouts, etc., for CS 106, CS 154, CS 260, and CS 162; and CS 260 as taught by D. Knuth (Box 13)
  - TeX test runs for "Notes on Programming in PASCAL" (Box 13)
  - Drafts of writings, 1984-92 (Box 13)
  - Auxiliary material to Pascal MS (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous note cards (Box 13)
  - Tony Lin for RWF – computations (Box 13)
  - Exposition of sterling numbers – notes (Box 13)
  - Readings in GKP for CS 260 (Box 13)
  - "Notes on Programming in Pascal," 1980 – 2 editions plus file of notes and drafts (Box 13)
  - File on algorithms (?) (Box 13)
  - Drafts of "Notes on Programming in Pascal" (Box 14)
  - RWF – handouts (2 folders) (Box 14)
  - Masters (course handouts ?) (Box 14)
  - CS 162 Winter 1982/83 – problems, answers, handouts, etc. (Box 14)
  - CS 262 Winter 1985/96 – problems, answers, handouts, etc. (Box 14)
  - CS 162 1984/85 – problems, answers, handouts, etc. (Box 14)
  - CS 162 Winter 1983-84 – problems, answers, handouts, etc. (Box 14)
  - Floyd – diagrams (Box 14)
  - CS 358 Aut. 1985/86 – problems, answers, handouts, etc. (Box 14)
  - R.W. Floyd – biography and misc. correspondence (Box 14)
  - CS 154 Spring 1981 – problems, answers, handouts, etc. (Box 14)
  - Notes for Language of Machines (Box 14)
  - Evaluating RWF 1988-89 (Box 14)
  - Report 1990-91 [contains only a flier on RWF talk] (Box 14)
  - GKP notes (Box 14)
  - Files (2) re account monies (Box 14)
  - Contracts / publishers (Box 14)
  - Papers in preparation (Box 14)
  - Indices – Files for 106, 254, 262, 257, BKG (Box 14)
  - "Program Verification" by Cliff Jones, 1991 – correspondence and text (Box 14)
  - Travel and phone (Box 14)
  - CS 106H – past students (Box 14)
  - Math/Comp Science – BS (Box 14)
  - CS 106H - – problems, answers, handouts, etc. (Box 14)
  - Assorted ".tex files" containing a mix of graphs and text (Box 14)
  - Files for Chapters 1 through 9 containing notes (Box 14)
  - Faculty evaluation reports [student assessments of his courses] 1982-1993 [several folders] (Box 15)
  - Pages 32-118 of textbook or course reader (Box 15)
  - Text for CS 106 book? (Box 15)
  - CS 106H handouts, Aut. 1984/85 (Box 15)
  - CS 154/254 – problems, answers, handouts, etc. (Box 15)
  - Manuscript notes and writings [1 folder] (Box 15)
  - CS 106 – problems, answers, handouts, etc. (Box 15)
  - RWF, "Programming and the Chiron Language," 1971 (Box 15)
  - SC106H – Class Note 1, Oct. 7, 1987; Class Note 2, Oct. 16, 1987 (Box 15)
  - Notebook on CS 204, 1976-72 [now in 3 folders] (Box 16)
  - Array.tex (stratified sampling on squares and cubes), 1984 (Box 16)
  - Course evaluations (Box 16)
  - RWF, "Guide to Chiron" (Box 16)
  - Furick, Bob – correspondence and related architectural drawings 1994-95 [re software for architectural uses] (Box 16)
  - CS 105 Spring 1976 taught by Mike Clancy, Jonathan King and Terry Roberts – class materials (Box 16)
  - SC 262 – manuscript notes, etc, 1988 (Box 16)
  - [Manuscript notes – unlabeled] (Box 16)
  - CS 106 – problems, answers, handouts, etc. (Box 16)
  - CS 106 handouts (Box 16)
  - Manuscript notes, unsorted [3 folders] (Box 16)
  - Cartoons (Box 16)
  - Computer printouts (Box 16)
  - Floyd – mail 1989 (mostly email) (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence 1994-95 (Box 16)
  - Files containing mostly manuscript notes on:
    - Hashing, coalesced (Box 16)
    - Hashing, linear (Box 16)
    - Hashing, other (Box 16)
    - Conditional expectations (Box 16)
    - Exam questions (Box 16)
    - Factorial moments (Box 16)
    - Normal functions #1 (Box 16)
    - Entropy (Box 16)
    - Normal functions #2 (Box 16)
    - RB trees (Box 16)
    - Cookie/coalesced/random walks (Box 16)
  - Manuscript notes, unlabeled (probably for class lectures, exams) [2 folders] (Box 16)
  - Evidence: P vs. T for doubles (Box 16)
  - Doubling – Algebraic Theory (Box 16)
  - Reprints: Articles by Floyd and others
    - Floyd, 1960s
      - A Note on Rational Approximation (Jan 1960) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - An Algorithm Defining ALGOL Assignment Statements (March 1960) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - An Algorithm for Coding Efficient Arithmetic Operations (Jan 1961) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - A Descriptive Language for Symbol Manipulation (Oct 1961) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - A Note on Mathematical Induction on Phrase Structure Grammars (Dec 1961) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Syntactic Analysis and Operator Precedence (July 1963) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Bounded Context Syntactic Analysis (Feb 1964) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - The Syntax of Programming Languages- A Survey (Aug 1964) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - New Proofs of Old Theorems in Logic and Formal Linguistics (Nov 1966) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Non-Deterministic Algorithms (Nov 1966) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Nondeterministic Algorithms (Oct 1967) (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - Assigning Meanings to Programs (1967) (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Floyd, 1970s
      - Linear Time Bounds for Median Computations (Aug 1971) (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Bounds on the Expected Time for Median Computations (Jan 1972) (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - An Interpretation-Oriented Theorem Prover over Integers (Aug 1972) (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Toward Interactive Design of Correct Programs (1972) (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Time Bounds for Selection and Expected Time Bounds for Selection (April 1973) (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - Time Bounds for Selection (Aug 1973) (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - A Linear Time Two Tape Merge (Dec 1973) (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - The Algorithm SELECT- for Finding the ith Smallest of n Elements [M1] (Sept 1974) (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - The Exact Time Required to Perform Generalized Addition (1975) (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - The Paradigms of Programming (1979) (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Floyd, 1980s
      - How Paul Magriel Almost Gave Up Backgammon (Spring 1983) (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Floyd, 1990s
      - Addition Machines (1990) (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Theory of Computation (March 1991) (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Assigning Meanings to Programs (1993) (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - The Language of Machines- An Introduction to Computability and Formal Languages (1994) (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Theory of Computation (April 1995) (Box 17, Folder 4)
      - Theory of Computation (small version) (April 1995) (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Floyd, undated
      - Can You Take a Double in a Symmetric Position? (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Notes on Programming Language (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - On Ambiguity in Phrase Structure Languages (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Permuting Information in Idealized Two-Level Storage (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Floyd, cover page
      - The Language of Machines- An Introduction to Computability and Formal Languages (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Abel, Gibbons, Josselyn, Musselman and Russell
      - Evaluation of Artificial Intelligence Technology in Surface Technology (U) (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Aristides
      - EI PMHN- To Rome (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Ferguson
      - The Mind’s Eye: Nonverbal Thought in Technology (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Hopkins, Singer and Strook
      - Current Developments in Mathematics, 1995 (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Kosaraju
      - Analysis of Structured Programs (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Context-free Preserving Functions (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - Probabilistic Automata- A Problem of Paz (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Leveson and Turner
      - An Investigation of the Therac-25 Accidents (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Backgammon game – problems (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Blank worksheets (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Backgammon correspondence (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Random walks (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Specific match positions (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Lecture + slide (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Program listings (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - [Backgammon miscellany] (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Running theory (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Backgammon problems (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Notes and drafts on racing (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - The Killer Heuristic (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Avoiding gammon (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - ACM folio with two certificates (Box 18)
  - Floyd and Richard Beigel, The Language of Machines; an introduction to computability and formal languages (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous magazines (Box 18)
  - Notecards (Box 18)
  - Set of slides labeled “IFIP 71” (Box 18)